Guide to the J. Walter Thompson Company. Wallace W. Elton Papers, 1909-1990
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
J. Walter Thompson Company. Wallace W. Elton papers 1909-1990
J. Walter Thompson Company.
9 linear feet Extent: 6,750 Items
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Durham, North Carolina 27708-0185
RL.00689
Language: English.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Access to some portions of the Wallace W. Elton Papers is restricted.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Wallace W. Elton Papers were transferred to the Special Collections Library by the J. Walter Thompson Company in 1987. An addition to the papers was donated by Jane Elton (Mrs. Wallace Elton) in 1991. Processing of this collection was supported in part by gifts from the J. Walter Thompson Company Fund and the John and Kelly Hartman Foundation.
Biographical Note
1907, Dec. 15 Born, Dorchester, Mass.
1929 Received a Ph.D. from Brown University; editor of The Brown Jug
1929-1939 Assistant Art Director, NW Ayer & Son advertising agency, Philadelphia, Pa.
1935 Married Mary Helen Birchard
1941 Senior Art Director, J. Walter Thompson Company and Lennen and Mitchell agencies, New York
1942-1945 Lt. Commander, United States Naval Reserve
1945, Dec. Director, Art Department, (rehired) J. Walter Thompson Company
1950 Elected Vice President, J. Walter Thompson Company
1952-1961 Copy Supervisor, Elected Vice President, J. Walter Thompson Company
1952- Creative Group Head, J. Walter Thompson Company
1956 Elected to the Board of Directors, J. Walter Thompson Company
1960-1964 Member of the Executive Committee, J. Walter Thompson Company
1961 Elected Executive Vice-President, J. Walter Thompson Company
1963 Elected Senior Vice-President, J. Walter Thompson Company
1965 International Executive Service Corps advertising and marketing advisor in Taiwan; leave of absence from J. Walter Thompson Company
1966 Retired from the J. Walter Thompson Company; Vice President, International Executive Service Corps (1966-1987)
1967- Brown University, Regional Director of Associated Alumni; Alumni Trustee; Regional Vice President of Associated Alumni
1977 Married Jane Vrooman Rice
1984 Inducted into Art Directors Hall of Fame
1991, Feb. Died, Coral Gables, Fla.
Wallace W. Elton was a member of the following advertising and art organizations: the National Society of Art Directors, the New York Art Director's Club, and the American Association of Advertising Agencies, Eastern Region Chairman.
Collection Overview
The papers of Wallace W. Elton span the years 1909 to 1990, although the bulk of the material dates from the 1940s to the 1960s. They consist of correspondence, memoranda, financial records, advertisements, military records, reports, photographs, drawings and other artwork, diaries, scrapbooks, memorabilia, printed material, and clippings. The collection documents the career of Elton; advertising history, especially agency management and the role of the creative director; and the automobile industry, especially advertising campaigns. Clients of the J. Walter Thompson Company represented in the collection include Chesebrough-Pond's, Ford Motor Company, and Pan American World Airways.
Aspects of Elton's education, his service in the United States Navy, his career, and professional projects and associations, including the International Executive Service Corps, are documented in the Personal Series. An alumnus of Brown University, Elton was active in the affairs of the university from about 1967 to 1985. The Personal Series includes correspondence with Brown University's president and others. The series includes advertisement proofs from NW Ayer & Son, where Elton directed the art and layout work for the Atlantic Refining Company, the Ford Motor Company, and other accounts. After resigning from the J. Walter Thompson Company, he became a Vice President for the International Executive Service Corps [IESC], a non-profit group formed to help improve the performance of private enterprises in developing countries. Detailed diaries recorded during Elton's IESC travel describe his work for the organization and include original illustrations. There are also newspaper accounts of IESC activities.
The bulk of the Personal Series documents Elton's executive roles in the J. Walter Thompson Company's corporate administration and the creative departments. Company policies, administrative issues including change in the organization, recruitment, and marketing plans are documented. In personal notes, Elton recorded his private observations about the management of the company and client relations. His interest in the history of the company continued after his retirement and is demonstrated in his participation in Retired Directors Reunions and contributions to the J. Walter Thompson Company Archives Fund. Materials that document Elton's work with J. Walter Thompson Company clients or campaigns are in the Clients Series and the Advertisements Series. While the former focuses on administrative issues in the creative process and the later series focuses on the advertisements and other graphic materials, there is considerable overlap between these two series.
The Clients Series documents communications with clients; the development and production of advertisements and campaign implementation; campaign presentations; and marketing schemes. Call reports record meetings or other communications with clients and are scattered throughout the files. The collateral material, which includes brochures, package and label designs, and other point-of-sale materials, were parts of advertising campaigns created to supplement display advertisements in magazines and newspapers and outdoor advertising. They were given directly to consumers or distributed by the clients.
The Ford Motor Company is the subject of the bulk of the Client Series. Since the Detroit Office of the J. Walter Thompson Company is responsible for the Ford account, a substantial amount of correspondence and memoranda from this office is in the series. It documents the interplay between the creative team in the New York office and account management in the Detroit office, and thereby demonstrates features of J. Walter Thompson Company corporate organization. Correspondence and memoranda from Norman H. Strouse document his management of the Ford Motor Company account in Chicago. Some campaigns were developed as lengthy projects, for example "Project X," an around-the-world tour for the 1958 Ford, and entailed extensive planning and time to accomplish. The Ford Motor Company files include documentation for all phases of such projects, including security measures to preserve the secrecy of the project during the planning phases. "Project M" developed around the concept of using Princess Grace [Grace Kelly] and the palace at Monaco to introduce the 1963 1/2 model year cars. The J. Walter Thompson Company negotiated an agreement between the Ford Motor Company and United Feature Syndicate for use of the services of Charles M. Schulz and the rights to use Schulz's Peanuts comics characters in advertising. The subsequent work executed for the Ford Motor Company's Falcon model is described in the Clients Series and the advertisements are in the Advertisements Series.
Most of the advertisements in the Advertisements Series are from Elton's personal portfolio. For many of the advertisements in the series, he was responsible for the creative idea for the ad copy. Elton sometimes depicted himself, and his wife, as characters in the advertisements. Insight into the creative process and the agency-client relationship can be studied through editorial notes attached to the advertisements or accompanying textual materials which provide information about the campaign or the artwork. A scrapbook contains photographic reproductions of older advertisements paired with tear sheets and proofs of contemporary advertisements developed by J. Walter Thompson Company. Ford Motor Company automobile models were advertised during the year preceding their introduction on the market and, although the publication dates are printed on most of the advertisements, the model year is not always obvious. Several Chrysler Corporation (competitive) advertisements are interfiled with the Ford materials. Norman Rockwell was the artist for some of the Pan American World Airways advertisements. The history of outdoor advertising can be studied from materials in the Personal Series, Advertisements Series, and Pictures Series.
Some of the portraits of Wallace W. Elton in the Pictures Series are by photographer Yousuf Karsh. J. Walter Thompson Company executives and staff are depicted at meetings and social events. Henry Ford and Edsel Ford and various models of Ford Motor Company cars, trucks and tractors are also depicted. In addition to photographs in the Pictures Series, there are photographs of Wallace Elton and International Executive Service Corps activities in the Personal Series.
Subject Headings
Ford Motor Company; Chesebrough-Pond's.; Pan American World Airways; Advertising executives; Advertising -- Management; Advertising agencies -- New York; Advertising agencies -- Michigan -- Detroit; Advertising campaigns; Advertising -- Automobiles -- United States; Advertising, Outdoor; Art directors; International Executive Service Corps; Brown University; Diaries; Commercial art; Elton, Wallace W.; Schulz, Charles M.; Strouse, Norman H.; Karsh, Yousuf, 1908-; John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History
Contents of Collection
- Personal Series, 1929-1990, undated (bulk 1946-1976).
  Includes correspondence, memoranda, advertisement proofs, artwork, military records, diaries, notes, scrapbooks, photographs, clippings, printed material and reprints, and memorabilia. See also oversize materials. Arranged by subjects which reflect the chronology of Wallace W. Elton's education and career path: Brown University, NW Ayer & Son, United States Navy, the J. Walter Thompson Company, and the International Executive Service Corps. The J. Walter Thompson Company materials are arranged alphabetically by folder title within the subject.
  - Brown University (Box 1)
    - Alumni activities, 1967-1985, undated (Box 1)
    - The Brown Jug, cover illustration by Wallace W. Elton, 1929, June (Box 1)
  - NW Ayer & Son: (Box 1)
    - Atlantic Refining Co., advertisement proofs with illustrations by Elton ("3 Little Men"), 1934 (Box 1)
    - Ford Motor Company, watercolor sketches by James Williamson, undated (Box 1)
  - United States Navy: (Box 1)
    - Officer Service Record, 1942-1955, undated (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous, 1943-1954, undated (Box 1)
  - J. Walter Thompson Company: (Box 1)
    - American Association of Advertising Agencies Convention, 1958, Apr. 24-26 (Box 1)
    - Biographical Files (Wallace W. Elton), 1949-1966, undated (Box 1)
    - Board of Directors, 1987-1988 (Box 1)
    - Building Decor: Memoranda from Margaret Tempest, 1960-1963 (Box 1)
    - Clippings: (Box 1)
    - 1964, 1989 (Box 1)
    - Creativity, 1961-1962, undated (Box 1)
    - Company policies, 1956-1957, undated (Box 1)
    - Outdoor Advertising: 18th National Competition and Exhibit of Outdoor Advertising Art, sponsored by Art Directors Club of Chicago (dismantled scrapbook), 1950 (Box 1)
    - "Out From Behind the Drawing Board" (Art Department), undated (Box 1)
    - Resignation, correspondence, 1966, Feb. (Box 1)
  - J. Walter Thompson Company: (Box 2)
    - Retired Directors Reunion at Duke University (May 25-27, 1990) and Contributions to J. Walter Thompson Company Archives, 1990, undated (Box 2)
    - Retirement, financial planning, 1957-1976 (Box 2)
    - T-Square, undated (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous, 1952-1966, undated (Box 2)
  - International Executive Service Corps: (Box 2)
    - Scrapbook (dismantled), 1966-1971 (Box 2)
    - Travel diary, 1965-1969, (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - Travel diaries and illustrations, 1968-1971 (removed from binder) (Box 2)
    - Travel diary, 1970-1971 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous, 1965-1976, undated (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous: (Box 3)
    - 1951-1970, undated (Box 3)
    - American Yacht Club, The First Hundred Years of American Yacht Club, Wallace W. Elton, Chairman of the Editorial Board, 1983 (Box 3)
- Clients Series, 1946-1964, undated (bulk 1951-1964). (Box 3)
  Includes correspondence, memoranda, artwork and storyboards, scripts, marketing proposals, meeting agendas and minutes, budgets and lists of expenses, itineraries, reports, contracts, notes, speeches, ad copy, awards, scrapbooks, photographs, memorabilia, clippings, and printed material. See also oversize materials. Arranged alphabetically by names of clients. Clients with extensive material are further arranged chronologically and then by subject categories relating to special projects or topics within the chronology.
  - American Petroleum Institute, 1962 (Box 3)
  - Beecham Products, 1961 (Box 3)
  - Blue Cross/Blue Shield (United Medical Service), 1961-1963, undated (Box 3)
  - Chesebrough-Pond's: (Box 3)
    - 1963, (2 folders) (Box 3)
    - 1962-1963, undated, Prince Matchabelli (Box 3)
    - 1963, undated, Cutex (Box 3)
  - Chesebrough-Pond's: (Box 4)
    - 1963-1964, Angel Face Cosmetic Products (Box 4)
    - 1963-1964, Creams (Box 4)
  - Crocker-Anglo National Bank, ca. 1960-1961, undated, (2 folders) (Box 4)
  - Crocker-Citizens Bank, 1963, Apr.-Nov., undated, (2 folders) (Box 4)
  - Crocker-Citizens Bank, 1963; Labatt, 1963 (Box 4)
  - Congoleum Nairn, 1961-1962, undated (Box 4)
  - Eastman Kodak Company, 1956-1963, undated (Box 4)
  - Ford Motor Company, 1946-1950, (7 folders) (Box 5)
  - Ford Motor Company, 1951-1953, (7 folders) (Box 6)
  - 1953: Ford Motor Company at Fifty (Box 6)
  - Ford Motor Company, 1954-1955, (5 folders) (Box 7)
  - Ford Motor Company: (Box 8)
    - 1956-1957: 1957 Retractable Hardtop (Box 8)
    - "Project X": 1957, Apr.-1958, (8 folders) (Box 8)
  - Ford Motor Company: "Project X": World Highways Expedition trophy, 1957 (Box [box 9 removed])
    [Trophy removed to the JWT Artifacts and Memorabilia Collection, Box AM13]
  - Ford Motor Company: (Box 10)
    - "Project X": 1958, May: Documentary script, "One Road," 1958, May (Box 10)
    - "Project Y": 1957, Aug.-Dec. (Box 10)
    - 1958 Campaign: First Program marketing presentation booklet, 1957, July (Box 10)
    - 1958, July (Box 10)
    - 1958, Aug.-Nov., Brussels World's Fair, (2 folders) (Box 10)
    - 1959-1961, May, Charles M. Schulz and "Peanuts" characters (Box 10)
  - Ford Motor Company: (Box 11)
    - Charles M. Schulz and "Peanuts" characters: (Box 11)
    - 1959, Oct.-Nov., Contract with United Features Syndicate (Box 11)
    - 1961, June-1963, General (Box 11)
    - 1963-1964, Contract Amendment (Box 11)
    - 1963, Documentary Film by Lee Mendelson (Box 11)
    - 1964, undated, General (Box 11)
    - 1960, Plans for 1964 World's Fair (Box 11)
    - 1961-1963, "Project M": (Box 11)
    - 1961-1962, n.d, Background information for Aug. 9, 1962 meeting (Box 11)
    - 1962, June-Sept., "Project M", (3 folders) (Box 11)
  - Ford Motor Company: (Box 12)
    - "Project M": (Box 12)
    - 1962, July, Report :"Project M: An advertising and promotion opportunity for the introduction of the 1962 1/2 cars" (Box 12)
    - 1962, Oct.-1963, Apr., (2 folders) (Box 12)
    - 1962, Nov.-1963, May: Union with Ferrari (Box 12)
    - 1963, Jan.-Aug., (3 folders) (Box 12)
  - Ford Motor Company: (Box 13)
    - 1963, Sept.-1964, (4 folders) (Box 13)
    - undated, "Product Philosophy Report,", (3 folders) (Box 13)
  - Ford Motor Company: (Box 14)
    - Advertising Awards, 1956-1960 (Box 14)
    - Collateral literature: (Box 14)
    - 1953-1964, undated, (3 folders) (Box 14)
    - Color and upholstery samples, 1959 (Box 14)
    - Competitors (Lincoln-Mercury), 1955 (Box 14)
    - Ford Dealers Association, 1962, Sept.-Nov., undated (Box 14)
  - Ford Motor Company: (Box 15)
    - Outdoor advertising: (Box 15)
    - "National Outdoor Advertising Awards, 1934 to date," 1962 (dismantled scrapbook), (3 folders) (Box 15)
    - Designs for billboards, 1948-1955, undated (Box 15)
  - Institute of Life Insurance, 1961-1963, (2 folders) (Box 15)
  - Jones Dairy Farm, undated (Box 15)
  - Labatt, 1963, undated (See also Crocker Citizen Bank) (Box 15)
  - Lever Brothers Company: Lux Toilet Soap, 1963, Apr. (Box 15)
    - Unilever Conference on Creative Advertising, 1962-1963, undated (Box 15)
    - Unilever Conference on Creative Advertising-Speeches, 1962 (Box 15)
  - Liggett & Meyers Tobacco Co., 1962-1963, (2 folders) (Box 16)
  - Massachusetts Mutual Life Insurance Co., 1962-1963 (Box 16)
  - Meredith Publishing Company, 1962-1963, undated (Box 16)
  - Pan American World Airways: Collateral literature, undated (Box 16)
  - R.T. French, 1960-1962, undated (Box 16)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 16)
- Pictures, 1909-1990, undated (bulk 1930-1990). (Box 16)
  Includes photographs, a set of reproductions, captions, and press releases. See also oversize materials. Arranged into personal, clients, and miscellaneous sections.
  - Personal: (Box 16)
    - Elton, Wallace W., 1909-1969, undated (Box 16)
    - NW Ayer, U.S. Navy, International Executive Service Corps, Retired Directors, 1930s-1990, undated (Box 16)
  - Personal: (Box 17)
    - People, including Wallace W. Elton and J. Walter Thompson Company staff, 1964-1983, undated (Box 17)
    - Art Directors Club Hall of Fame, presentation about Wallace W. Elton, 1984 (Box 17)
    - Art Directors Club Hall of Fame Election Dinner, 1985, Dec. (Box 17)
  - Clients: (Box 17)
    - Ford Motor Company: (Box 17)
    - Automobiles, undated (Box 17)
    - Henry Ford and Sons, 1930-1959, undated (Box 17)
    - Ford Falcon-"Peanuts" group, including Charles M. Schulz, 1960 (Box 17)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 17)
- Advertisements Series, 1946-1963, undated (Box 17)
  Chiefly color advertising proofs and tear sheets, some with correspondence, memoranda, and notes attached; pencil and chalk sketches and roughs; photographs; and a scrapbook. Arranged alphabetically by client; the Ford Motor Company is arranged in chronological order according to model year.
  - Old Friends and New, undated (dismantled scrapbook): (Box 18)
    - (Clients: Chesebrough-Pond's; Douglas Aircraft Co.; Eastman Kodak Co.; Fanny Farmer Candy Shops; Florida Citrus Commission; Ford Motor Co.; J.B. Williams Co.; Kraft Foods Co.; Kraft-Phenix Cheese Corp.; Lever Brothers; Libby, McNeill & Libby; Oneida; Pan American World Airways; Penick and Ford\Vermont Maid; Pineapple Growers of Hawaii; Radio Corporation of America\RCA Victor; R.T. French Co.; Scott Paper Co.; General Time Corp.\Seth Thomas Clocks; Shell Oil Co.; Swift & Co.; U.S. Brewers; U.S. Marine Corps; and United States Lines) (Box 18)
  - P. Ballantine & Sons, 1953; Chrysler, undated; Crocker-Anglo National Bank, ca. 1960; Crocker-Citizens Bank, 1963; Florida Citrus Commission, 1951-1952 (Box 18)
  - Ford Motor Company: (Box 18)
    - 1946-1958, (4 folders) (Box 18)
    - Charles M. Schulz's "Peanuts" characters, 1960-1963 (Box 18)
  - Ford Motor Company: Early Models (by NW Ayer & Son), undated (Box 18)
  - Labatt, 1963; Massachusetts Mutual Life Insurance Company, 1963 (Box 18)
  - Pan American World Airways, 1953-1957 (Box 18)
  - J. Walter Thompson House Advertisements, 1951 and 1956 (Box 18)
  - Ford Motor Company: (Oversize-box 19, Box 18)
    - 1950-1963, (4 folders) (Box 18)
    - Charles M. Schulz's Peanuts characters, 1960-1963 (Box 18)
  - Pan American World Airways, 1953-1957 (Box 18)
- Oversize Materials (Box 18)
  - Personal Series (Box 18)
    - J. Walter Thompson Company: (Oversize-box 19, Box 18)
      - Outdoor Advertising: 18th National Competition and Exhibit of Outdoor Advertising Art, Art Directors Club of Chicago (dismantled scrapbook), 1950, Feb. 14-15 (Box 18)
    - J. Walter Thompson Company: (Oversize-box 18, Box 18)
      - Cy Klauck drawings (gift to Wallace Elton), 1959 (Box 18)
      - Opening of Pittsburgh Office, signed booklet, 1961 (Box 18)
    - International Executive Service Corps, 1982-1984 (Box 18)
  - Clients Series (Box 18)
    - Chesebrough-Pond's, 1963; Eastman Kodak, 1950 (Oversize-box 18, Box 18)
    - Ford Motor Company: (Box 18)
      - Brussels World's Fair, 1958; Project M, 1962; 1963 Model: The Big Change.. ., Ford Motor Company supplement to the Chicago Tribune, 1963, April 4; Advertising Awards, 1951-1955; Collateral Literature, 1939-1954?; Ford Dealers Association, 1962; Outdoor Advertising: 1949; "National Outdoor Advertising Awards, 1934 to date," (dismantled scrapbook), 1962 (Box 18)
    - Ford Motor Company: (Opaperfolder 1, Box 18)
      - Charles M. Schulz and "Peanuts" characters, 1961-1963 (Box 18)
      - Collateral literature, 1955-1963 (Box 18)
      - Marty Links and Bobby Sox, 1947 (Box 18)
      - Seat belt safety, Ford Safety Story Blankets Nation, 1955 (Box 18)
    - Personal: (Oversize-box 18, Box 18)
      - Elton, Wallace W. by Yousuf Karsh, undated (Box 18)
      - Brown University, Miscellaneous, undated (Box 18)
    - Clients: (Box 18)
      - Ford Motor Company: Automobiles, 1965 (Box 18)